<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: feynman | Side Notes]]></title>
  <link href="http://blog.ndpar.com/categories/feynman/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://blog.ndpar.com/"/>
  <updated>2017-01-08T17:14:02-05:00</updated>
  <id>http://blog.ndpar.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Andrey Paramonov]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Another Notation as a Tool of Thought]]></title>
    <link href="http://blog.ndpar.com/2015/04/03/feynman-tot/"/>
    <updated>2015-04-03T08:00:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://blog.ndpar.com/2015/04/03/feynman-tot</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>In his seminal <a href="http://www.jsoftware.com/papers/tot.htm">paper</a> Kenneth Iverson described a new mathematical notation which soon became A Programming Language.</p>

<p>Recently, while reading <em>Surely You’re Joking, Mr. Feynman!</em>, I found that Feynman invented his own notation when he was in school.</p>

<!-- more -->

<blockquote>
  <p>While I was doing all this trigonometry, I didn’t like the symbols for sine, cosine, tangent, and so on. To me, $\sin f$ looked like $s$ times $i$ times $n$ times $f$! So I invented another symbol, like a square root sign, that was $\sigma$ with a long arm sticking out of it, and I put the $f$ underneath. For the tangent it was $\tau$ with the top of the tau extended, and for the cosine I made a kind of $\gamma$, but it looked a little bit like the square root sign.</p>
</blockquote>

<blockquote>
  <p>Now the inverse sine was the same sigma, but left-to-right reflected so that it started with the horizontal line with the value underneath, and then the sigma. <em>That</em> was the inverse sine, NOT $\sin^{-1} f$–that was crazy! They had that in books! To me, $\sin^{-1}$ meant $1/\sin$, the reciprocal. So my symbols were better.</p>
</blockquote>

<blockquote>
  <p>I didn’t like $f(x)$–that looked to me like $f$ times $x$. I also didn’t like $dy/dx$–you have a tendency to cancel the d’s–so I made a different sign, something like an &amp; sign. For logarithms it was a big L extended to the right, with the thing you take the log of inside, and so on.</p>
</blockquote>

<blockquote>
  <p>I thought my symbols were just as good, if not better, than the regular symbols–it doesn’t make any difference <em>what</em> symbols you use–but I discovered later that it <em>does</em> make a difference. Once when I was explaining something to another kid in high school, without thinking I started to make these symbols, and he said, “What the hell are those?” I realized then that if I’m going to talk to anybody else, I’ll have to use the standard symbols, so I eventually gave up my own symbols.</p>
</blockquote>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
